Finding Aid for George W. Shepherd papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George W. Shepherd papers 1919-1965 1919-1939
Shepherd, George W.
3 linear feet and 2 maps (in 1 tube)
2014151 Aa 2
George W. Shepherd was a Congregationalist missionary in China with the New Life Movement from 1919-1939 and advisor to Chiang Kai-Shek; married to Dr. Clara (Sargent) Shepherd. The collection includes George Shepherd's writings about his experiences in China, family correspondence, sermons and lectures, and material from the New Life Movement.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was received from Jay J. Pease, Jr. (donor no. 11126 ) in August 2011.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George W. Shepherd served as a Congregationalist missionary in China between 1919 and 1939 during which time he became intimately involved in that country's political workings. Shepherd worked mainly in the Fukien region, though he traveled due to professional assignments and the political climate. Shepherd became proficient in the Chinese language and worked to spread Christianity around the Chinese countryside.
During Shepherd's time as a missionary China experienced much political turmoil. Both the Communist and Nationalist parties raised armies and fighting broke out across China as both factions sought dominance. Chiang Kai-Shek, the leader of the Nationalist party, gained control of the country in 1928. The Nationalists were largely anti-Western and anti-Communist and instead embraced Confucianism and other traditional Chinese influences.
Shepherd's close connection with Chinese politics developed during the latter half of his time in China as the result of his work with Chiang Kai-Shek's wife, known as Madame Kai-Shek, and the New Life Movement she supported. The New Life Movement sought to blend Chinese moral values found in Confucianism along with some Christianity and had a heavy nationalist influence. George Shepherd focused primarily on the Christianity piece and sought to spread Christianity to as many Chinese citizens as possible through the New Life Movement.
George Shepherd and his family eventually had to leave China in 1939 because of the looming Second World War; however he continued to speak about his time in China and even wrote a book that was never published about his experiences. He also collected his letters and writings from the time and kept them together. His wife Dr. Clara Sargent Shepherd wrote about the family's experiences in an unpublished memoir.
The papers consist of two series: Writings and New Life Movement in China Materials.
The George W. Shepherd papers provide an intimate look at Chiang Kai-Shek and China through the eyes of a Congregationalist minister. The papers also document the experience of a missionary family living in China between 1919 and 1939. This collection will be used by those seeking information about China from an American/Australian Christian perspective during a time of great change within China. Shepherd's writings include correspondence, memoranda, notes, and manuscript of Shepherd's book about Chiang Kai-Shek and China. The New Life Movement in China materials include promotional materials, photographs, maps, and missionary records.
Subjects:
Chiang, Kai-Shek 1887-1975.; China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Politics and Government-- 1912-1949.; Social conditions.; Missionaries--China--20th century.; New Life Movement.; Shepherd, George W.; Shepherd, Clara Sargent.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Agricultural laborers.--China--20thcentury.; China--Maps.; Missionaries--China--20th century.; Students--China--20th century.
Contributors:
Shepherd, Clara Sargent.
Genre Terms:
Maps.; Photographs.
- Writings, 1919-1943, 1965
  The Writings series (1919-1943; 2 linear feet) contains material written by, with, or to George Shepherd. Of particular note are a typed memoir that Dr. Clara Sargent Shepherd wrote about the family's life in China and several drafts of an unpolished book by Shepherd about his time working with Chiang Kai-Shek. The manuscript and memoir are based largely off of correspondence included in this series, both original handwritten and typed letters. Other items include lecture and sermon notes with topics such as prayer, character, and the significance of holidays, personal memorandum books, and notes on Christian mission work including building a new world and other topics.
  - Correspondence, 1919-1939, 13 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscript, after 1939, 5 folders (Box 1)
    (Shepherd's book about Chiang Kai-Shek)
  - Memoir: "Yours in the Bonds of Love" by Clara Shepherd
    - 1965 (Box 1)
    - After 1939, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Memorandum, 1934, 1938 and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Notes on General Missions, 1940 and undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Sermon and Lecture Notes, 1943 and undated, 8 folders (Box 2)
- New Life Movement in China Materials, 1919-1943
  The New Life Movement in China Materials series (1919-1943; 2 linear feet) holds materials regarding Shepherd's work with the New Life Movement while he was in China. This includes promotional booklets and published materials about China as well as some of Shepherd's materials from working with Chinese citizens. Also included are some of Shepherd's travel in China materials with dates of travel. The series also contains photographs of Chinese citizens, Chiang Kai-Shek and his wife, and Shepherd himself. In addition there are two oversize maps of China in this collection, one made in the United States date unknown, and one made in China in 1938.
  - Christian Mission Materials, 1938, 1941 and undated, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Maps
    - New Map of China, 1938 (Tube 1)
    - Map of China, undated (Tube 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1919-1939, 9 folders (Box 3)
  - Promotional Materials, 1931, 1935-1942 and undated, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Travel Materials 1930-1941 (Box 3)
Related Material
For other related material see the University of Stanford's Hoover Institute's George W. Shepherd papers.